<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writing on Michel Mooij</title>
    <link>https://michelmooij.github.io/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Writing on Michel Mooij</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2017 Michel Mooij</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://michelmooij.github.io/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Technology and Environment</title>
      <link>https://michelmooij.github.io/writing/technology-and-environment/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelmooij.github.io/writing/technology-and-environment/</guid>
      <description>Context for New Ways of Working
Usually, it is not customer needs, that set the specifications for the development of technology. It is the marketing of an emerging technology that arouses the client’s desire. Developpers of new gadgets like smart phones and tablets responded to potential needs, which manifested when the possibilities of the new technology emerged. We have allowed the smartphones into our lives, changing our communication and work behavior to adapt to the new opportunities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Intelligence, Big Data and the Distribution of Wealth</title>
      <link>https://michelmooij.github.io/writing/ai-bigdata-and-the-distribution-of-wealth/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2017 17:10:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michelmooij.github.io/writing/ai-bigdata-and-the-distribution-of-wealth/</guid>
      <description>Is the free market is still able to steer the production and distribution of goods and services to sustain a peaceful society or is it time to replace it by a new economic system which uses AI to distribute the wealth with algorithms and big data?
Animal Robots, by Henk Mooij 1930-2015
Artificial Intelligence (AI), I would rather call it high intelligence because it is not so much the artificiality that matters, but the fact that it will soon be superior to human intelligence.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>